Guide to the Daniel Huntington Study Portrait Photographs Collection ca. 1870-1890 PR 256
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Daniel Huntington Study Portrait Collection
ca. 1870-1890
PR 256
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.42 Linear feet (141 photographs, 12 folders)
The collection holds 141 portrait photographs used by Huntington for his study of the subjects painted by him.
Provenance
Gift of Charles R. Huntington, April 9, 1908.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Daniel Huntington (1814-1906) was educated at Hamilton College. He studied panting with Samuel Morse and Henry Inman in New York City. He primarily painted portraits and landscapes. Huntington was president of the National Academy of Design, and Vice-President of the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
Scope and Content Note
Two years after Daniel Huntington's death, his son Charles Richards Huntington (1847-1915) presented the New-York Historical Society with a collection of 141 portrait photographs used by his father "for his study of the subjects painted by him." Each of the men (and the single woman, Mary McCrea Stuart) in the collection is represented by one or more portrait photographs which had been blown-up to life-size dimensions, sometimes made from a previously existing negative or one made of an earlier photograph. In the case of sitters who died before the advent of paper photography, images were taken from daguerreotypes. The enlargements were mounted on a stiff paperboard and roughly trimmed almost to the shape of the subject's head. Each of the portraits has the sitter's surname in pencil on the verso; some have a shorthand clue to an occupation, profession, title, or institutional affiliation. These annotations, if contemporary to Huntington or his son, have been transcribed in the box and folder list that follows. Many of the photographs have a puncture at their top, most likely from the nail Huntington used to tack them up in view of his easel.
The sitters are familiar to students of nineteenth-century New York: they include prominent bankers, merchants, industrialists, educators, financiers, generals, lawyers, judges, politicians, government officials, and men of the cloth. The photographs are generally not dated. Several note that they were made from daguerreotypes and a few mention particular photographers, or are mounted on the backs of printed boards from photographers' studios. The images that are dated range from the 1870s (Henry Potter) to the 1890s (Kelly, Gracie, Schurz, and Sheldon). Photographers mentioned are Bogardus (Adams, Arthur) and Sarony (Tilden), with one annotated by Huntington as having been taken in his studio (Sherman). Eight of the portraits are mounted on the verso of stamped boards from the Rockwood Studio (Brown, Gracie, Johnston, Henry Potter, Taft, and Weir) or Kurtz (Dodge Sr. and Hostetter) in New York. In addition, the portrait of Henry Codman Potter is mounted on the verso of a large photograph of Calvary Baptist Church, on West Twenty-third Street.
Oil portraits of these sitters are now in the New York Chamber of Commerce Collection at the New York State Museum, the Smithsonian Institution, Metropolitan Museum of Art, the American Museum of Natural History, New York Public Library, Harvard University, Vassar College, and West Point Museum, among other institutions. The New-York Historical Society owns more than twenty portraits painted by Huntington. Other portraits remain in private collections, including those of social clubs, hospitals, corporations, and the families who commissioned them from the artist.
Arrangement
Photographs are filed alphabetically by sitter; life dates and vocations were added during processing.
Huntington, Daniel, 1816-1906.; Men -- Portraits.; Photographic prints.; Portraits.
- Portraits
  Scope and Contents note
  Portraits are filed alphabetically by sitter; life dates and vocations were added during processing.
    - Adams, William (1813-1897), clergyman (Folder 1)
      General note
      On verso:(taken by Bogardus photographer)
    - Arthur, Chester Alan (1830-1886), politician
    - Aspinwall, William Henry (1807-1875), businessman
    - Avery, Samuel Putnam (1822-1904), art dealer, philanthropist
    - Babcock, Samuel D. (1822-1902), banker
    - Beardsley, Samuel (1790-1860), judge, politician
      On verso: (perish commerce perish credit)
    - Blatchford, Samuel (1820-1883), judge
    - Booth, Henry Matthias (1843-1899), clergyman, educator
      On verso: of Auburn [Theological Seminary]
    - Brown, James (1791-1877), banker
    - Brown, James M. (1820-1890), banker
    - Bruce, George (1781-1866), typefounder
      On verso: from daguerreotype
    - Cameron, James Donald (1833-1918), politician (Folder 2)
      On verso: Senator Cameron, Sec of War
    - Chittenden, Simeon Baldwin (1814-1889), merchant
    - Clark, Luther C. (d. 1877)
    - Colgate, Robert (1812-1885), merchant
    - Coxe, Arthur Cleveland (1818-1896), clergyman
      On verso: Bishop of Western New York (Buffalo)
    - Curtiss, Cyrus (d. 1879), merhcant [2 images]
      On verso: of Washington Life Insurance Co.?
    - Davis, Noah (1818-1902), judge
    - Dodge, William E., Sr. (1805-1883), merchant
    - Dodge, William E., Jr. (1832-1903), businessman [2 images]
    - Drisler, Henry (1818-1897), educator
      On verso: Prof
    - Dwight, Theodore W. (1822-1892), educator [3 images]
      On verso 1 & 2: of Columbia Law School; on verso 3: of Law School Columbia
    - Edwards, Henry Pierrepont (1809-1855), judge (Folder 3)
      On verso: (from a Daguerre)
    - Field, Benjamin Hazard (1814-1893), philanthropist
    - Field, Cyrus West (1819-1892), capitalist [2 images]
      On verso #2: capital likeness D.H.
    - Fry, Charles M. (1822-1892), merchant, bank president
      See: Folder 12
    - Frelinghuysen, Frederick Theodore (1817-1885), politician [2 images]
    - Gallatin, Albert (1761-1849), politician, diplomat
      On verso: from a daguerreotype
    - Gardiner, John Lyon (1841-1920), gentleman
    - Garrison, Cornelius K. (1809-1885), businessman [2 images]
      On verso: "Com"[modore]
    - Gracie, James King (1840-1903), philanthropist
    - Hallgarten,Julius (1842?-1884), banker (Folder 4)
      On verso: from the small photo
    - Hamilton, Alexander, Jr. (1816-1889), lawyer
      On verso: afterward President of Astor Library Trustees
    - Hastings, Thomas S. (1827-1911), clergyman
    - Hayes, Rutherford Birchard (1822-1893), politician [3 images]
      On verso #2: after his presidency
    - Hoffman, Eugene Augustus (1829-1902), clergyman, educator [2 images]
      On verso: Dean Hoffman
    - Hoffman, Samuel Verplanck (1802-1880), lawyer
      On verso: father of Dean H. of the Seminary
    - Hostetter, David Herbert (1819-1888), manufacturer
    - Hunt, Wilson G. (1804-1892), merchant
    - Jacobi, Abraham (1830-1919), doctor, educator (Folder 5)
    - James, Daniel Willis (1832-1907), merchant
    - Jesup, Morris Ketchum (1830-1908), financier [2 images]
    - Johnston, John Taylor (1820-1893), railroad president
    - Jones, John Divine (1814-1895), businessman
      On verso: Pres of Atlantic Ins. Co.
    - Kelly, Eugene (1806-1894), banker
      On verso: 1891
    - Kelly, William (1807-1872), philanthropist
    - Kendrick, Henry L. (1812-1891), educator
      On verso: of West Point
    - Kennedy, Robert Lenox (1822-1887), banker [2 images]
      On verso #2: too severe - but very like
    - King, Richard (d. 1891), businessman
      On verso: Prest of Bank of Commerce
    - Lauterbach, Edward (1844-1923), lawyer, politician (Folder 6)
    - Lenox, James (1800-1880), philanthropist
      On verso: This is quite large enough rather larger than life
    - Lincoln, Robert Todd (1843-1926), lawyer, politician
      On verso: (son of Prest Lincoln Secy of War)
    - Low, Abbot Augustus (1843-1912), inventor
    - Low, Seth (1850-1916), educator, politician [2 images]
      On verso #1: when Prest of Columbia
      On verso #2: Pres. Columbia University & Mayor of N.Y. & Bklyn
    - Lyman, Theodore Benedict (1815-1993), clergyman
      On verso: Bishop of N Carolina
    - McGee, James (d. 1898), businessman
    - McLane, James Woods (1839-1912), doctor, educator
      See: oversize
    - Martin, Charles Jackson (d. 1888), businessman
      On verso: Prest Home Insurance
    - Mills, Darius Ogden (1825-1910), banker
    - North, Edward (1820-1903), educator
      On verso: Prof Ham College
    - Nye, Ezra (1798-1866), sea captain
      [from a daguerreotype]
    - Owen [Owens?], Thomas J. (d. 1881?), shipping merchant (Folder 7)
      On verso: painted June 1882 taken from another (much earlier) photograph
    - Parker, Amasa Junius (1807-1890), judge
    - Phelps, John Jay (1810-1869), merchant
      On verso: father of Wm Walter Phelps [1839-1894]
    - Phelps, Royal (1809-1884), merchant
      On verso: he was in bad health & died soon after this was taken
    - Pierrepont, Henry Evelyn (1808-1888), philanthropist
      On verso: of Brooklyn NY
    - Potter, Henry Codman (1834-1908), clergyman
      On verso: of Grace [Church] (about 1875)
    - Prentice, Ezra Parmalee (1797-1876), businessman
      On verso: of Albany
    - Prime, William Cowper (1825-1905), lawyer, educator
      On verso: V Prest of Metr Mus of Art
    - Pruyn, Robert Lansing (1825-1906), businessman
    - Raven, Anton Adolph (1843-1919), businessman
      On verso: of Atlantic Mutual Ins Co.
    - Ray, Robert (1794-1879), banker
    - Rolston, Roswell Graves (1838-1898), businessman
      On verso: Prest Farmers Loan & Trust Co.
    - Roosevelt, Theodore Sr. (1831-1878)
    - Sage, Henry Williams (1814-1897), businessman, philanthropist (Folder 8)
      On verso: of Ithaca
    - Schermerhorn, William Colford (1821-1903), philanthropist
    - Schurz, Carl (1829-1906), politician, diplomat
      On verso: 1899
    - Schwab, Gustav (1822-1888), businessman
    - Scott, Thomas A. (1823-1881), railroad man
      On verso: of Philada (before his paralysis)(good likeness)
    - Sheldon, James O. (1823-1907), banker
    - Sheridan, Philip Henry (1831-1888), military
    - Sherman, John (1823-1900), politician [2 images]
      On verso #1: taken in my studio DH
      On verso #2: taken when Secy of the Treasury
    - Sibley, Hiram (1807-1888), industrialist, philanthropist (Folder 9)
      On verso: (died July 1888)
    - Silliman, Benjamin (1805-1901), lawyer
      On verso: Council for Bank of Commerce too old (when taken) but about right for him now 1888 / yes-good yet in 1898
    - Smith, Gerrit (1797-1874), philanthropist
    - Stokes, James Boutler (1804-1881), banker
      On verso: father of Anson Phelps Stokes
    - Stranahan, James Samuel Thomas (1808-1898), politician
      On verso: (of Brooklyn)
    - Stuart, Robert L. (1806-1882), merchant, philanthropist [3 images]
    - Stuart, Mary McCrea [Mrs. Robert L.] (d 1891), philanthropist
    - Sturges, Jonathan (1802-1874), merchant
    - Sutherland, Jabez Gridley (1825-1902), judge
    - Taft, Alphonso (1810-1891), politician
    - Thomas, Lewis (d. 1880), grain merchant (Folder 10)
      On verso: (of Produce Exchange)
    - Thompson, David (d. 1871?), businessman
      On verso: NY Life & Trust?
    - Tibbits, George Moritimer (1796-1878), gentleman
      On verso: Troy [NY]
    - Tilden, Samuel Jones (1814-1886), politician [2 images]
      On verso #1: fm Saronys port photo
    - Tracy, Edward H. (d. 1875), engineer
    - Travers, William Riggin (1819-1887), financier
    - Trimble, George Thomas (1793-1872), merchant
    - Trimble, Merritt (1824-1903), banker
      On verso: "Bank for Savings" N.Y.
    - Vail, Henry F. (1812-1881), banker [2 images]
      On verso: Prest Bank of Commerce
    - Vail, Thomas Hubbard (1812-1889)
    - Vanderbilt, Cornelius II (1843-1899) [2 images]
      On verso #1: does not do him justice too old & severe
      On verso #2: not long before his attack [1896] a strong likeness
    - Vanderpoel, Aaron (1799-1870), judge
    - Warren, John (1799-1878), stockbroker (Folder 11)
      On verso: Prest of Board of Brokers (Stock Exchange)
    - Warren, J. Kearney (d. 1895)
    - Washburn, Edward Abiel (1819-1881), clergyman
      On verso: of Calvary Church
    - Weir, Robert Walter (1803-1889), painter
    - Whipple, Henry B., Rev. (1822-1901), clergyman
      On verso: Bishop / He said "it looked like a Methodist parson" yet it is a tremendous likeness D.H.
    - White, Andrew Dickson (1832-1918), diplomat
      On verso: President of Cornell about 1890, minister to Germany 1899
    - White, Chandler (d. 1856) [from a daguerreotype]
      On verso: of the first Cable Syndicate This is from an old daguerreotype of the only likeness to be found of him
    - Whittingham, William Rollison (1805-1879), clergyman, Bishop of Maryland
      On verso: This is severe (as it should be) from the Daguerreotype / fine for character (but it was very hot weather & his shirt-collar showed it)! (not a bad Savonarola) D.H.
    - Williams, John S. (1814-1876), businessman
      On verso: of Williams & Guyon [Guion]
    - Winthrop, Robert (1832-1892), banker
      On verso: of New York
    - Winthrop, Robert Charles (1809-1894), lawyer [2 images]
      On verso #1: very good before he began to grow feeble
    - Wolfe, John David (1792-1872), merchant [2 images]
    - Woodruff, Lewis Bartholomew (1809-1875), judge
      On verso: Lewis B. US Circuit Court
    - Washburn, Edward Abiel (1819-1881), clergyman
    - Washburn, Edward Abiel (1819-1881), clergyman
- Oversize Portraits
  Filed alphabetically by sitter; life dates and vocations were added during processing.
    - Fry, Charles M. (1822-1892), merchant, bank president (Folder 12)
      On verso: President of Bank of NY taken about 1888-90 he died Nov 1892
    - Gardiner, John Lyon (1841-1910), gentleman
    - Gracie, James King (1840-1903), philanthropist
      On verso: 1878
    - Johnston, John Taylor (1820-1893), railroad president
      On verso: Capital Likeness DH
    - McLane, James Woods (1839-1912), doctor, educator
      On verso: June 1898 / Dr. J.W. McLane / Pres of Trustees College Physicians & Surgeons / James W. McLane MD
    - Pruyn, Robert Lansing (1852-1906), businessman
    - Taft, Alphonso (1810-1891), politician
    - Tracy, Edward H. (d. 1875), engineer
    - Trimble, George Thomas (1793-1872), merchant
      On verso: NY Hospital?
    - Weir, Robert Walter (1803-1889), painter